Guide to the Hartwell Family Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Hartwell Family Papers
1846-1975
RG 4
Yale University Divinity School Library
7.5
(23 boxes)
Dating from 1849-1972, these papers span three generations of Baptist mission involvement and pioneer activity. Jesse Boardman Hartwell, 1795-1859, was the patriarch of the Hartwell family of Baptist missionaries, although not a missionary himself. He served as pastor of various Baptist churches across the United States, professor at Howard College, Marion, Alabama in 1844, and president and professor of theology at Mt. Lebanon University in 1857. His son, Jesse Boardman Hartwell, Jr., 1835-1912, graduated from Furman University, Greenville, S.C. in 1855. He served as professor of mathematics at Mt. Lebanon University and became a China missionary in 1858. He organized the first Protestant church in China north of Shanghai and was active in helping refugees during the Tai Ping rebellion, 1851-1864. Four of J.B. Hartwell, Jr.'s children were active in China missions, including daughters Nellie, Anna (Canton, Tengchow and Hwanghsien) and Lottie (Shaohing and Hangchow, Cheking Province). Son Charles Norris Hartwell was educated at the China Inland Mission Schools in Chefoo and the State University of Missouri. He was appointed to the Southern Baptist Convention's North China Mission in 1909. He served as principal of the Boys' High School in Hwanghsien and, at the time of his death in 1927, was Dean of North China Baptist College.
Hartwell family
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lottie Hartwell Ufford, 1969, 1975, 1976.
Biographical / Historical
Jesse Boardman Hartwell, founder of this Baptist missionary family, was born in Buckland, Massachusetts, on May 2nd, 1795. Little is known of hls parents, Jesse and Jerusha Hartwell, except that his father was active in the ministry for over sixty-six years.
Baptized by his father in 1815, Jesse B. Hartwell received a license to preach the gospel the following year, and entered Brown University with the goal of becoming a missionary to India. Although he never reached the foreign field, Hartwell maintained a life-long interest in missions. He remained in Providence, R. I. after graduating with the Class of 1819 and undertook a three year pastorale at the Second Baptist Church. During this period he married Maria Thayer, who died within a few years, although the exact date of her death is unknown. The couple had one child.
Due to failing health, Hartwell moved to Charleston, South Carolina, in 1822 and married Margaret Forman Brodie two years later. At least seven children were born of this marriage, including a son, J. Boardman Hartwell, Jr., in 1835. (The following are children of Jesse B. Hartwell: Ann Hartwell Alison, Charles M. Hartwell - d. l857, (Edward?) Hartwell, Elizabeth Hartwell - d. l852, Ellen C. Hartwell Edwards (Mrs. Robert G.), Jesse Boardman Hartwell, Jr. - b. l835 - d. 1912, Maria R. Hartwell Haynes (Mrs. Edward), and Mary Helen Hartwell Gibbs. One child, possibly Maria Haynes, was born during Hartwell's marriage to Maria Thayer. His second wife, Margaret Forman Brodie Hartwell, is the mother of the other children.)
Between l822-1836, the elder Jesse Hartwell served at various local churches in South Carolina and became a professor at "Furman Theological Institution" (now Furman University, Greenville, S.C.) In December 1836, the family moved to Alabama, where he was elected President of the Baptist State Convention three years later. His approximately nine years in office were particularly critical ones, for Baptists from the North and South clashed over the subject of abolition and the refusal of Northern Boards to appoint slaveholders to foreign or domestic mission fields. In l845, he and James C. Crane served jointly as first secretary of the Southern Baptist Convention. The University of Alabama conferred the D.D. degree upon him the same year.
In addition to his other activities, Hartwell became Professor of Theology at Howard College, Marion, Alabama, in 1844 and President of the Domestic Mission Board, Southern Baptist Convention.
In 1848, the Hartwells moved to the Arkansas frontier where Jesse Hartwell conducted the Camden Female Institute until becoming President and Professor of Theology at Mt. Lebanon University in 1857. During his two years at Mt. Lebanon, he also served as President of the Louisiana Baptist Convention. He died in September 1859.
When Jesse Hartwell came to Mt. Lebanon University, his son, J. Boardman Hartwell, had already been appointed Professor of Mathematics at the same institution. An 1855 graduate of Furman University,Greenville, S.C., young Hartwell achieved his father's goal by becoming a missionary in 1858. (Furman University later awarded J. Boardman Hartwell the D.D. degree.) Before sailing for the Orient, he married Eliza Jewett of Macon, Georgia. The couple spent their first year in Shanghai,
moved to Chefoo in 1860, and then settled in Tung Chow, where Hartwell remained until 1875.
It is interesting to note that during this time:
"Mr. Hartwell baptized the first man in Shantung province; he organized the first Protestant church in China north of Shanghai;...perhaps the first foreign contribution ever made to missionary work came in 1869 to the Southern Baptist Convention from his North Street Church in Tung Chow." (Annual Minutes of the Baptist State Convention, South Carolina Baptist Convention, 1912, p. 110.)
During the Tai Ping rebellion (1851-1864), Hartwell devoted himself to the Chinese people: "At one time for nearly six weeks he had on his premises one hundred refugees, to whom he acted as surgeon, nurse, and preacher; dangers beset him and his; more than once he was forced to put himself under the protection of the United States Consul, and on one occasion he and his family were forced to flee on horseback to save their lives." (Ibid. p. 110.)
In 1870, Hartwell was left a widower with four children, including infant twins. (The children of J. Boardman and Eliza Jewett Hartwell are: Anna B. Hartwell (b.1870-d.1961), Carrie Hartwell (b.d. c.1861-1864), Jesse George Hartwell (b.1860-d.1932), John Holzendorf Hartwell (b.1870d. c. 1871), Maggie Hartwell (b.d. 1870), "Nellie" Edwards Hartwell Beattie (b.1863-?). Anna and John Hartwell were twins. "Nellie's" first name is probably "Ellen". The children of J. Boardman and Charlotte Norris Hartwell are: Charles Norris Hartwell (b.1884-d.1927), "Lottie" Hartwell Ufford (b.1882-?), "Lottie" may be a nickname for "Charlotte". Two other children, Claude Hartwell (b. c. 1893-d. before 1927) and Jane Hartwell (b. c. 1890) may be the offspring of Charlotte W. Norris Hartwell by a previous marriage.) He returned briefly to America the following year, and married Julia Jewett, the sister of his first wife. Widowed again eight years later, Hartwell became a missionary to the Chinese community in San Francisco, California. He was appointed superintendent for Chinese missions on the Pacific Coast by the American Baptist Home Mission Society, married Charlotte W. Norris the next year, and returned to China in l893. He died in China in 1912, after fifty-four years of foreign and domestic missionary service.
The Hartwell missionary tradition continued through a third generation, as four of J. Boardman Hartwell's children worked in China. Nellie Hartwell married Presbyterian missionary Andrew Beattie, and the couple served together until 1908. Anna Burton Hartwell graduated from the Baptist Missionary Training School in Chicago in 1891, and worked briefly among the Chinese in San Francisco, California, before being appointed to China by the Baptist Foreign Mission Board in l892. She performed evangelical and educational work at Canton, Tengchow, and Hwangheien. Lottie Hathaway Hartwell graduated from Wellesley College, Wellesley, Massachusetts, and married A. Frank Ufford, a graduate of the University of Vermont and Andover Newton Theological Seminary. From 1908 to 1941, the Uffords worked together under the auspices of the American Baptist Foreign Mission Society in Shaohing and Hangchow, Cheking Province. Mr. Ufford was engaged in promotional work for the Society in New York City from 1942 to 1946. The couple returned to China in 1946 for two years of special service. Mr. Ufford died sometime in the mid 1950's.
Charles Norris Hartwell was born in San Francisco, California, but grew up in Tung Chow and prepared for college at the China Inland Mission Schools, Chefoo. He graduated from the State University of Missouri, taught in the United States for several years, and married Elizabeth ("Bessie") Hartwell. He was appointed by the Southern Baptist Convention to its North China Mission in 1909, and immediately became principal of the Boys' High School in Hwanghsien. At the time of his death in 1927 he was Dean of North China Baptist College.
The following additional biographical information is contained in the material given by Lottie Hartwell Ufford in 1976.
Charlotte Elizabeth Norris, born in Baltimore July 19, 1849, married Jesse Hartwell in 1881 while Mr. Hartwell was the superintendent for the Chinese Mission in San Francisco's Chinatown. Charlotte, third wife Jesse Boardman Hartwell, and mother of Lottie Hathaway, Charles Norris, Claude and Jane, died in 1903 having been in China for ten years.
The four children, born in San Francisco, went to China with their parents 1892. Lottie finished school at the China Inland Mission School in Chefoo before coming to the United States with her brother Charles for a preparatory year at Mrs. Potter's Private School for Girls in Everett, Massachusetts. The summer before she went to Wellesley College, while working as a waitress, she received word that Claude had died of ptomaine poisoning in China in 1902. (Box 22, Folder 12. Photographs re. Family.)
While attending a missionary rally in Boston, Lottie was "impressed" with chairman, A. Frank Ufford, who had volunteered to go to China during the Boxer Rebellion. Lottie and Frank Ufford were married in 1906 and sailed for China in 1908. One daughter was born to them, Nina (later called Betty), who married Herbert Dean. (Box 19, Folder 2. Biographical material.)
An additional biographical fact which has come to light from the added material is: John Holzendorf Hartwell, twin brother of Anna B. Hartwell, "grew to manhood and went to Australia. Died there." (Box 21, Folder 12. Photographs re. Family.)
Scope and Contents
I. Correspondence: Family, 1849-1972.
II. Correspondence: General, 1852-1969.
III. Writings, 1852-1953.
IV. Personal Items and Memorabilia.
Dating from 1849 to 1975, these papers span three generations of Baptist mission involvement and pioneer activity. It is also interesting to note the constant westward mobility of the Hartwells - from New England, to the South, the Arkansas frontier, and finally China.
The first series, CORRESPONDENCE: FAMILY, is also the most extensive. CORRESPONDENCE: FAMILY contains letters exchanged between virtually every member of the immediate Hartwell Family from 1849 to 1972. The contents of the correspondence vary greatly according to generation. The letters of Jesse and Margaret Forman Hartwell contain parental advice and local color, while those of their son, J. Boardman Hartwell, concern travel and domestic affairs. Most complete, and perhaps most interesting, are those letters exchanged between Hartwell and his first wife, Eliza Jewett Hartwell during their courtship in America and married life in China. The letters of the third generation are few, but include those written during childhood and adulthood. Correspondence to and from various relatives of the Hartwell's is also included in this section.
Frontier life, slavery, the Civil War and Reconstruction are parts of American history documented throughout this section. Correspondence written from China reveals anti-foreign sentiment, mission history, and living conditions.
The second series, CORRESPONDENCE: GENERAL houses letters written both to and from friends and associates of the Hartwell Family. With the exception of letters written by A. Frank Ufford, husband of Lottie Hathaway Hartwell, there is little written by members of the family. Among the most interesting material in this section are two letters written by "J.S. Murrow'' to Eliza Jewett Hartwell from "Indian Territories, Creek Nation" in 1857 and 1858.
The third series, WRITINGS, contains a variety of material, the earliest being a group of sermons attributed to Jesse Hartwell, Sr. dated from 1852 to 1858. Two possible essays are the sole writings of J. Boardman Hartwell. The life and personality of Anna B. Hartwell are reflected in her private "notebooks", which span the years 1889-1944. Inserted in these diary-like writings are correspondence, clippings, and poetry. The writings of A. Frank Ufford include printed articles, notes, possible sermons, addresses by others, and two notebooks kept in Shaohing, China. Several folders contain reports prepared by Ufford and others, including the annual reports of the East China Baptist Mission. The typed manuscripts of this missionary primarily concern Christianity, Communism, China, travel, and his work in East China. Two lengthy manuscripts are also housed in this section: "The Burning Bridge", a 16 chapter autobiography and interpretation of twentieth century China by A. Frank Ufford, and the 87-page memoir "China in Retrospect" by K.K. Thompson.
PERSONAL ITEMS AND MEMORABILIA, the final series, contains genealogical and biographical information regarding the Hartwells, Chinese leases or deeds which belonged to J. Boardman Hartwell, and a variety of other material.
A. Frank Ufford's collection of "interesting autographs" spans the years 1910-1951. Much of the material bears the letterheads of Baptist organizations or educational institutions, and occasionally letters are addressed to Lottie Hartwell Ufford.
A section of photographs,located at the end of the series, includes photographs of the Hartwells, and their fellow missionary Harry Luce with his young son, Henry. Recent Chinese history is documented by two 1937 photographs depicting the burning of the Chapei section of Shanghai by the Japanese. Leafs from a photograph album show mission work in Shaohing.
Arrangement
I. Family Correspondence, 1849-1972
II. General Correspondence, 1852-1969
III. Writings, 1852-1953
IV. Personal Items and Memorabilia
Baptists; Frontier and pioneer life; Missions -- China; Missions; Slavery; Clergy; Deans; Educators; Missionaries; Hartwell, Anna Burton, 1870-1961; Hartwell, Charles Norris, 1884-1927; Hartwell, Jesse Boardman, Jr., 1835-1912; Ufford, Lottie Hathaway Hartwell, 1882-; Hartwell family; American Baptist Foreign Mission Society; Southern Baptist Convention. Foreign Mission Board
- Correspondence: Family, 1849-1972; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Jesse Boardman Hartwell, Sr. (JBH, Sr.)
  Margaret Forman Hartwell (MFH)
  J. Boardman Hartwell (JBH)
  Eliza Jewett Hartwell (EJH)
  Julia Jewett Hartwell (JJH)
  Charlotte W. Norris Hartwell (CWNH)
  Anna Burton Hartwell (ABM)
  Bessie Hartwell
  Charles Norris Hartwell (CNH)
  Claude B. Hartwell
  Jane G. Hartwell
  Jesse G. Hartwell
  Nellie E. Hartwell (Beattie)
  A. Frank Ufford (AFU)
  Lottie Hartwell Ufford (LHU)
  Ann J. Hartwell Alison (AJHA)
  Ellen C. Hartwell Edwards (ECHE)
  Robert G. Edwards (RGE)
  Mary Helen Hartwell Gibbs (MHHG)
  - JBH, Sr. to "children", JBH, 1849, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - JBH, Sr. to JBH, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - JBH, Sr. to JBH, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - JBH, Sr. to JBH, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - JBH, Sr. to JBH, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - JBH, Sr. to JBH, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - JBH, Sr. to JBH, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - JBH, Sr. to "children", JBH, MHG, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - JBH, Sr. to JBH and EJH, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - MFH to "children", JBH, 1850, 1852, 1854, 1855, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - MFH to JBH, and EJH, 1858-1860 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - MFH to "children" (JBH and EJH), 1866, 1868,1870, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - EJH to JBH, 1858 Jul-Sep (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - EJH to JBH (1863?), 1861 Jan, Feb (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - EJH to JBH, 1864 Mar-Apr (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - EJH to JBH, 1864 May (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - EJH to JBH, 1864 Jun (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - EJH to JBH, 1864 Jul (Box 2, Folder l8)
  - EJH to JBH, 1864 Aug-Sep (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - EJH to JBH, 1867 May, c. 1866-1868 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - EJH to JBH, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - EJH to JBH, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - EJH to JBH, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - EJH to JBH, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - EJH to JJH, 1854, 1858 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - EJH to JJH, 1859 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - EJH to JJH, 1860, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - JBH to JBH, Sr.; the Hartwell Family in general, 1851, 1859, 1860 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - JBH to MFH, 1859, 1861 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - JBH to MFH, 1863, 1867, 1868 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - JBH to EJH, 1858 Jul-Aug (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - JBH to EJH, 1858 Sep (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - JBH to EJH, 1859 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - JBH to EJH, 1861, 1863 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - JBH to EJH, 1863 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - JBH to EJH, 1864 Mar (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - JBH to EJH, 1864 Apr 17-28 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - JBH to EJH, 1864 Apr 4-18 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - JBH to EJH, 1864 May 1-6 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - JBH to EJH, 1864 May 8-25 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - JBH to EJH, 1864 Jun 1-14 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - JBH to EJH, 1864 Jun 21-29 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - JBH to EJH, 1864 Jul 3-13 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - JBH to EJH, 1864 Jul 15-31 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - JBH to EJH, 1864 Aug 3-7 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - JBH to EJH, 1864 Aug 13-28 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - JBH to EJH, 1864 Sep (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - JBH to EJH, (1864?), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - JBH to EJH, 1865 Jul (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - JBH to EJH, 1865 Aug (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - JBH to EJH, 1866 Nov; 1867 Jan, May (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - JBH to EJH, 1867 Oct (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - JBH to EJH, 1868 Dec; 1869 May, Dec (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - JBH to EJH, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - JBH to JJH, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - JBH to JJH, 1871 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - JBH to his children: ABH, ABH, LHU, ONE, Hartwell, Jesse George, 1864, 1895, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - JBH to ABH, 1894, 1897 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - JBH to his sisters: MHHG, 1852, 1860 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Haynes, Maria Hartwell, 1864, 1873 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - unidentified "sister", 1899 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - JJH to EJH, 1850 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - JJH to JBH, 1871 May-Jun (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - JJH to JBH, 1871 Jul (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - JJH to JBH, 1871 Aug (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - JJH to JBH, 1871 Sep (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - JJH to JBH, 1871 Oct (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - JJH to JBH, 1871 Nov 1-12 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - JJH to JBH, 1871 Nov 16-29, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - CWNH to ABH, 1894, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - CWNH to ABH, 1897, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - CWNH to "Janie", "Claude", "dear ones", 1894, 1897 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - CNH to "Nannie", 1894 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - CNH to AFU, AFU-LHU, and Nina, 1927 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - ABH to Hartwell, Bessie, 1921 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - ABH to CNH, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - ABH to Hartwell, Claude, 1894 (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - ABH to LHU, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - ABH to LHU-AFU, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - ABH to LHU, 1927 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - ABH to unidentified cousin, 1919 (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - ABH from unidentified cousins, illegible signatures, 1961, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Hartwell, Bessie to ABH, 1921, 1923 (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Hartwell, Bessie to LHU, 1927 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Hartwell, Claude B. to ABH, JBH, JBH-CWNH, 1899, 1901 (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Hartwell, Jane G. to ABH, JBH (1897?), 190S, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Hartwell, Jesse George to JBH, JJH, 1871 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Hartwell, Nellie E. (Beattie) to JJH, 1870 (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - LHU to "Nannie", 1893, 1894 (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - "Darling", 1897 (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - "Sisters", "Sister", 1923, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - LHU to "Nannie", 1897 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - LHU to "My Darling," "My Precious," "Sister", 1897, 1940, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - LHU to "Sisters", 1941 (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - LHU to "Sister", 1946-1948, 1952 (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - LHU to BH, 1929 (Box 18, Folder 15)
  - LHU to "Betty and Herb", 1947, 1948 (Box 18, Folder 16)
  - LHU to AFU, 1922, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 17)
  - AFU to LHU, 1927 (Box 18, Folder 18)
  - AFU to LHU, 1932-1934 (Box 18, Folder 19)
  - AFU to LHU, 1935 (Box 18, Folder 20)
  - AFU ("Jip") to LHU ("Mistress"), 1927 (Box 18, Folder 21)
  - AFU to LHU and Betty, 1934 (Box 18, Folder 22)
  - AFU to his daughter, Nina, 1927 (Box 18, Folder 23)
  - AFU to his daughter, Betty, 1933-1935, 1947 (Box 18, Folder 24)
  - AFU to "Betty and Herb", 1938-1941, 1947, 1948 (Box 18, Folder 25)
  - AFU to "Dear Folks", 1947 (Box 18, Folder 26)
  - AFU to "Sister", 1941, 1947, 1948, 1952 (Box 18, Folder 27)
  - AFU to "Jane", 1947, 1948 (Box 18, Folder 28)
  - LHU to "Janie dear", 1948 (Box 18, Folder 29)
  - Hartwell, Jane to LHL, 1952 (Box 18, Folder 30)
  - (Beattie), Ernest and Dorothy to LHU, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 31)
  - LHU ("Aunt Lottie"): Corres. rec'd., 1952, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 32)
  - "Aunt Helen" to LHU and Betty, 1934 (Box 18, Folder 33)
  - AJHA to JBH and MHHG, JBH, 1850-1853 (Box 6, Folder 78)
  - AJHA to JBH, 1854-1857 (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - AJHA to JBH, 1859, 1860, 1867, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - (Allson?), Bet to JBH; Alison, Hartwell; Alison, Martha C., 1857, 1871, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 81)
  - ECHE to JBH, 1850, 1852-1853 (Box 6, Folder 82)
  - ECHE to JBH, 1854 Feb-Aug (Box 6, Folder 83)
  - ECHE to JBH, 1854 Sep-Nov (Box 6, Folder 84)
  - ECHE to JBH, 1855 (Box 6, Folder 85)
  - ECHE to JBH, 1856 (Box 6, Folder 86)
  - ECHE to JBH, 1857 (Box 6, Folder 87)
  - ECHE to JBH, 1858, 1859, 1861, 1864 (Box 6, Folder 88)
  - ECHE to JBH, 1866, 1867, 1869, 1870 (Box 6, Folder 89)
  - ECHE to JBH, c. 1850-1859 (Box 6, Folder 90)
  - ECHE to JBH, 1871, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 91)
  - ECHE to EJH, 1858 (Box 6, Folder 92)
  - ECHE to ABH, 1900 (Box 6, Folder 93)
  - Edwards, Hannah to ABH, c. 1869-1870 (Box 6, Folder 94)
  - Edwards, Janie Bessie to Hartwell, Nellie (Beattie), 1851 (Box 6, Folder 94)
  - RGE to JBH, 1853-1855 (Box 6, Folder 95)
  - RGE to JBH, 1856-1858 (Box 6, Folder 96)
  - Elisa ("Cousin") to JBH, 1854, 1856-1858 (Box 6, Folder 97)
  - Elisa ("Cousin") to JBH, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 98)
  - MHHG to JBH, 1852 (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - MHHG to JBH, 1854-1855 (Box 6, Folder 100)
  - MHHG to JBH, 1856 (Box 6, Folder 101)
  - MHHG to JBH, 1857 (Box 6, Folder 102)
  - MHHG to JBH. JBH and EJH, 1858-1859 (Box 6, Folder 103)
  - MHHG to JBH and EJH, JBH, 1860-1862, 1870 (Box 6, Folder 104)
  - MHHG to EJH, 1858 (Box 6, Folder 105)
  - MHHG to ABH, 1870 (Box 6, Folder 106)
  - Harriet (Aunt) to JBH, (1858?) (Box 6, Folder 107)
  - Harris, Mary Wellborn to EJH, 1859 (Box 6, Folder 105)
  - Hartwell, Charles M. to JBH, 1852-1857 (Box 6, Folder 109)
  - Haynes, Maria R. Hartwell to JBH, 1855, 1859, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 110)
  - Holzendorf, Eliza to EJH; Holzendorf, "John" to EJH, 1850, 1858 (Box 6, Folder 111)
  - Jewett, Charles R. to JBH, 1858, 1861, 1871 (Box 6, Folder 112)
  - Jewett, Charles R. to JBH, EJH, fragment, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 113)
  - Jewett, Charles R. to EJH, 1858, 1860 (Box 6, Folder 114)
  - Jewett, George to JJH; Jewett, Henry to EJH, JBH; Jewett, Susan to EJH, JBH, 1846, 1848, 1859, 1860, 1871, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 115)
  - Key, Jessie H. to JBH, 1909 (Box 6, Folder 116)
  - Pope, C. to JBH, 1871, 1872 (Box 6, Folder 117)
  - "Charlotte" to "Cousin Jo", 1926 (Box 18, Folder 34)
- Correspondence: General, 1852-1969; Series II